Welcome back to AP US history in under 3
minutes. No time for intros, let's get
into it. I said two things within my
past videos. First, I said slavery will
be the big issue until 1865. And second,
I said westward expansion would cause
the Civil War. In this period around
1800, we start seeing the start of this.
Migrants continuously moved west
searching for a new life. The issue of
this is that these migrants were
encroaching on Native American land.
This made Native Americans rethink their
alliance with the US and start something
known as the Northwest Indian War. And
rebel with some examples being St.
Clair's defeat and the Battle of Fallen
Timbers. Even the federal government had
attempted to test its federal power in
this frontier tension, imposing a
violent whiskey tax and prompting a
rebellion against it. In the expansion
westward, Britain took the side of
Native Americans and provided support
against the US, which would heighten
tensions between the US and Britain,
which would eventually cause another war
to break out. The other thing to mention
is the growing split between the north
and the south. We start seeing these two
areas separate on values around this
time. The main reason for this was
slavery. The south had slavery
implemented heavily throughout its
territories. And once it expanded
westward, more slavery was implemented.
This caused various anti-slavery
sentiments to arise, such as Gabriel's
Rebellion, where Virginia slaves
rebelled and it ended in a violent
suppression. Another example of this was
the Act for the gradual abolition of
slavery mentioned in previous videos.
But overall, even with the split
starting to emerge between the north and
the south, lots of historians argue that
this point in history was when Americans
were most unified. On the screen now are
AP style questions for this topic. Pause
now.
I'll put the answers on the screen now.
I will see you in unit four.